<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<info>
<title>Gists and the Gist API</title>
<date>2018-11-09</date>
</info>
<section xml:id="chapter2">
<title>Gists and the Gist API</title>
<simpara><indexterm>
<primary>gists</primary><secondary>id=ix_chapter-02-gist-asciidoc0</secondary><tertiary>range=startofrange</tertiary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>id=ix_chapter-02-gist-asciidoc0</primary><secondary>range=startofrange</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>range=startofrange</primary>
</indexterm>GitHub revolutionized software development by responding to a deep
desire to share information. But calling it just "sharing" does a disservice to
the tools GitHub provides: these tools remove barriers to
communication and streamline workflows. These tools also arose at
exactly the moment when the information technology revolution forced
companies to adopt more open technologies that assisted an emerging remote
workforce.</simpara>
<simpara>Gists service part of this need: they permit intimate code
sharing and reuse, refactoring, and experimentation in a way not served by the
heavyweight tools predating it. In this chapter we will explore using
gists to share code, and then build an application hosted as a
gist that uses the Gist API.</simpara>
<section xml:id="_easy_code_sharing">
<title>Easy Code Sharing</title>
<simpara><indexterm>
<primary>gists</primary><secondary>creating</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>creating</primary>
</indexterm>Gists are straightforward to create. You copy a snippet
of code into the large text box in the center, optionally enter in a
description or filename, and then choose between a public or private
gist. Once your gist has been created you are presented with a URL to
share. Gists autodetect the language in most cases and syntax
highlight according to the language when displayed as in <xref linkend="documenting_json_using_a_gist"/>.</simpara>
<figure xml:id="documenting_json_using_a_gist">
<title>Documenting JSON using a gist</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="images/btwg_02in01.png"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>btwg 02in01</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<simpara>There are other services that do this: pastebin was the first, and
there are many others that offer variances on code sharing. But gists
by GitHub are not simply a pasting service. Gists are first-class
repositories, forkable, editable, and expansive. We&#8217;ll go over the basics
of what gists are, and how to create them, and then show how they
allow you to share code that is also a live application.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_gists_are_repositories">
<title>Gists Are Repositories</title>
<simpara><indexterm>
<primary>gists</primary><secondary>as repositories</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>as repositories</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm>
<primary>repositories</primary><secondary>gists as</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>gists as</primary>
</indexterm>Every gist
created is a tiny repository. You can update gists and see
the history using<indexterm>
<primary>git log</primary>
</indexterm> <literal>git log</literal>. You can download gists, hack on the
repository, and<indexterm>
<primary>git push</primary>
</indexterm> <literal>git push</literal> them back into the repository on
<emphasis>gist.github.com</emphasis> (which will republish them onto the publicly
facing web page). And, you can "fork" gists, just like
any other repository.</simpara>
<simpara>You are allowed to branch within gist repositories; however, branches
are not displayed inside of <emphasis>gist.github.com/</emphasis>. But if you need the
benefits of branching when using gists you can branch normally
inside a repository and the branch information is retained on the
upstream repository after you push it up.</simpara>
<simpara>You can have an unlimited number of public and <indexterm>
<primary>secret gists</primary>
</indexterm>secret gists. Secret gists can, in many cases, replace private repositories, and these secret gists don&#8217;t count against the limited amount of private repositories you have with paid GitHub accounts. Or, you can make a<indexterm>
<primary>public gists</primary>
</indexterm> gist public, and
share that URL to mailing lists or anywhere you need public feedback.</simpara>
<note>
<simpara>As there are two types of gists (public and secret), it is important
to understand the differences between them. Public gists are
searchable. Secret gists are not searchable, but they are accessible
to anyone who knows the URL. Don&#8217;t post any code to a gist you
need to keep secret as once you put it there, it is only as safe as
the URL is secret.</simpara>
</note>
<simpara>Most people share gists through the URL, but you can embed gists
inside of other contexts (like blogs) and get a simple and pretty
snippet of code.</simpara>
<section xml:id="_embedding_gists_inside_html">
<title>Embedding Gists Inside HTML</title>
<simpara><indexterm>
<primary>gists</primary><secondary>in HTML</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>in HTML</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm>
<primary>HTML</primary><secondary>gists in</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>gists in</primary>
</indexterm>To embed inside of an HTML page look for the "Embed this gist" box to
the left of a gist. Copy the code listed there (which will look
something like <literal>&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/xrd/8923697.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</literal>) and paste it
into your HTML.</simpara>
<simpara>If you wish to include only a particular file from the gist (if it
contains multiple files), then add <literal>?file=hi.rb</literal> to the end of the
URL specified in the src attribute.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_embedding_inside_jekyll_blogs">
<title>Embedding Inside Jekyll Blogs</title>
<simpara><indexterm>
<primary>gists</primary><secondary>in Jekyll blogs</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>in Jekyll blogs</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm>
<primary>Jekyll blogs</primary><secondary>gists in</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>gists in</primary>
</indexterm>Jekyll blogs (explained in <xref linkend="Jekyll"/>) can easily host
gists using a special syntax. The shortcut <literal>{% gist 8138797 %}</literal> will
embed a private gist, which would be found at
<emphasis><link xl:href="http://gist.github.com/8138797">http://gist.github.com/8138797</link></emphasis>.  If you want to use a
specific file within the gist, add a filename to the gist code like
<literal>{% gist 8138797 hi.rb %}</literal>. Secret gists can also be embedded. If you
use a secret gist, prefix the username of the account holder in the
gist like so: <literal>{% gist xrd/8138797 hi.rb %}</literal>.</simpara>
<simpara>Now let&#8217;s look at creating gists from outside the GitHub.com site,
using the command-line.</simpara>
</section>
</section>
<section xml:id="_gist_from_the_command_line">
<title>Gist from the Command Line</title>
<simpara><indexterm>
<primary>command line</primary><secondary>gists from</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>gists from</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm>
<primary>gists</primary><secondary>from command line</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>from command line</primary>
</indexterm><literal>gem install gist</literal> <indexterm>
<primary>gem install gist command</primary>
</indexterm>will install a command line tool that helps create gists. You can use it simply by typing the command, and then
entering the data you want to post as a gist:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">$ gist
(type a gist. &lt;ctrl-c&gt; to cancel, &lt;ctrl-d&gt; when done)
{ "foo" : "bar" }
https://gist.github.com/9106765</programlisting>
<simpara>The gist command will return the link to the gist just created. Gists
are created anonymously by default. You can log in using the <literal>--login</literal>
switch. Once you do this, your gists will be linked to
your account:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">$ gist --login
Obtaining OAuth2 access_token from github.
GitHub username: xrd
GitHub password:
2-factor auth code: 787878

Success! https://github.com/settings/applications</programlisting>
<simpara>You can pipe text to the gist command to use the contents of that
file:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">$ echo '{ "foo" : "bar" }' | gist
https://gist.github.com/9106799</programlisting>
<simpara>You can also <literal>cat</literal> a file to gist:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">$ cat MyJavaFile.java | gist
https://gist.github.com/9345609</programlisting>
<simpara>Gists are often used to show interesting or troublesome code, and there
are times when you don&#8217;t want to display the entirety of a file. In
this case the command-line<indexterm>
<primary>grep tool</primary>
</indexterm> <literal>grep</literal> tool can be useful; <literal>grep</literal> searches
for a specific piece of code and with the right switches can include
several lines of context around that code inside a gist. This command
looks for the function <literal>myFunction</literal> inside the <emphasis>MyJavaFile.java</emphasis> file
and then prints the next 20 lines of context and stores it as a gist:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">$ grep -A 20 myFunction MyJavaFile.java | gist
https://gist.github.com/9453069</programlisting>
<simpara>Adding <indexterm>
<primary>&#8211;o switch</primary>
</indexterm>the <literal>-o</literal> switch automatically opens the gist inside your
default web browser. You can also copy the gist URL to the clipboard
using <indexterm>
<primary>&#8211;c switch</primary>
</indexterm>the <literal>-c</literal> switch. Or, you can copy the contents of your clipboard
into a gist using<indexterm>
<primary>&#8211;P switch</primary>
</indexterm> the <literal>-P</literal> switch.</simpara>
<simpara>There are many other fun features of the gist command. To learn more
run the gist command with<indexterm>
<primary>&#8211;&#8211;help switch</primary>
</indexterm> the <literal>--help</literal> switch.</simpara>
<simpara>As gists are themselves repositories, you can use them for dual
purposes: for hosting code samples, and for code samples that are themselves
fully working and packaged applications inside a gist repository.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_gists_as_fully_functioning_apps">
<title>Gists as Fully Functioning Apps</title>
<simpara><indexterm>
<primary>gists</primary><secondary>as fully functioning apps</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>as fully functioning apps</primary>
</indexterm>Let&#8217;s build a simple Sinatra application to showcase how code hosted
as a gist can also be a living application. <indexterm>
<primary>Sinatra</primary>
</indexterm>Sinatra is a Ruby library
for creating dead-simple web servers. A Sinatra program can be as
simple as this:</simpara>
<programlisting language="ruby" linenumbering="unnumbered">require 'sinatra'

get '/hi' do
  "Hello World!"
end</programlisting>
<simpara>Create a gist for this by visiting <a class="orm:hideurl" href="https://gist.github.com/"><em>gist.github.com</em></a>. Enter in the text exactly as shown and then choose
public gist.</simpara>
<simpara>You now have a share-friendly gist of code anyone can use to review.
More importantly, this is a repository with executable code. To clone
it, look for the Clone URL to the right of the gist itself. You will
likely see a Git protocol URL and an HTTPS URL. If you are cloning
the URL and intend only to read the gist, you can use the HTTPS
URL. You technically can push changes once you have cloned a
repository using the HTTPS URL but not if you have two-factor
authentication enabled. In most cases it is easier and more flexible
to use the Git protocol URL.</simpara>
<simpara>Let&#8217;s clone it now:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">$ git clone git@gist.github.com:8138797.git</programlisting>
<simpara>Once you have cloned the repository, go inside it. You&#8217;ll see a list
of files, a list that right now includes only one file:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">$ cd 8138797
$ ls
hi.rb</programlisting>
<simpara>This code is exectuable: to run it enter <literal>ruby hi.rb</literal>.</simpara>
<simpara>If you have not used Sinatra with Ruby before, this will cause an
error. This program requires a library called "sinatra" and
you have not yet installed it. We could write a read me file, or add
documentation into this file itself. Another
way to guarantee the user has the proper files installed is to<indexterm>
<primary>Gemfile</primary>
</indexterm> use a
<emphasis>Gemfile</emphasis>, which is a file that tells
which libraries are installed and from where. That sounds like the
best way:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">$ printf "source 'https://rubygems.org'\ngem 'sinatra'" &gt; Gemfile</programlisting>
<simpara>The <literal>bundle</literal> command (from the bundler gem) will install Sinatra and
the associated dependencies:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">$ bundle
Using rack (1.5.2)
Using rack-protection (1.5.1)
Using tilt (1.4.1)
Using sinatra (1.4.4)
Using bundler (1.3.5)
Your bundle is complete!
Use `bundle show [gemname]` to see where a bundled gem is installed.</programlisting>
<simpara>Why did we do things this way? Because now we can add the Gemfile to
our repository locally, and then publish into our gist for sharing on
the Web. Our repository now not only has the code, but a well-known
manifest file that explains the necessary components when running the
code.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_gists_that_render_gists">
<title>Gists that Render Gists</title>
<simpara><indexterm>
<primary>gists</primary><secondary>for rendering other gists</secondary><tertiary>id=ix_chapter-02-gist-asciidoc1</tertiary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>id=ix_chapter-02-gist-asciidoc1</primary><secondary>range=startofrange</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>range=startofrange</primary>
</indexterm>Let&#8217;s add to our application and use the<indexterm>
<primary>Octokit</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm>
<primary>Octokit Ruby</primary>
</indexterm> Octokit Ruby gem to pull all
public gists for any user we specify. The Octokit library is the
the official Ruby library for accessing the GitHub API. Why would we want to make a gist
that displays other gists? Self-referential meta code is all the rage, the
modern-day response to René Magritte&#8217;s famous work: "Ceci n&#8217;est pas une
pipe."<footnote><simpara><link xl:href="http://bit.ly/1Ot2qOd">Explained best by Ben Zimmer</link></simpara></footnote></simpara>
<simpara>Add a view <emphasis>index.erb</emphasis> at the root of our directory:</simpara>
<programlisting language="ruby" linenumbering="unnumbered">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;body&gt;

User has &lt;%= count %&gt; public gists

&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>
<simpara>Add the Octokit gem to our Gemfile:</simpara>
<programlisting language="ruby" linenumbering="unnumbered">gem "octokit"</programlisting>
<simpara>Run <literal>bundle</literal> to install Octokit. Then, modify our <emphasis>hi.rb</emphasis> app to look
like this:</simpara>
<programlisting language="ruby" linenumbering="unnumbered">require 'sinatra'
require 'octokit'

set :views, "."

get '/:username' do |username|
  user = Octokit.user username
  count = user.public_gists
  erb :index, locals: { :count =&gt; count }
end</programlisting>
<simpara>Our filesystem should look like this, with three files:</simpara>
<programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">$ ls -1
Gemfile
hi.rb
index.erb</programlisting>
<simpara>Restart Sinatra by running Ctrl-C and then <literal>ruby hi.rb</literal>. If you visit <emphasis><link xl:href="http://localhost:4567/xrd">http://localhost:4567/xrd</link></emphasis> in
your browser, you will see the count of public gists for user <literal>xrd</literal> (<xref linkend="displaying_the_gist_count"/>);
modify the username in the URL to specify any GitHub username and you will see
their last five gists displayed.</simpara>
<figure xml:id="displaying_the_gist_count">
<title>Displaying the gist count</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="images/btwg_02in02.png"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>btwg 02in02</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<section xml:id="_going_deeper_into_the_gist_api">
<title>Going Deeper into the Gist API</title>
<simpara><indexterm>
<primary>gists</primary><secondary>and hypermedia</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>and hypermedia</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm>
<primary>Hypermedia API</primary><secondary>gist and</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>gist and</primary>
</indexterm>The GitHub API uses hypermedia instead of
basic resource-driven APIs. If you use a client like Octokit, the
hypermedia details are hidden behind an elegant Ruby client. But
there is a benefit to understanding how hypermedia works when you need
to retrieve deeper information from the GitHub API.</simpara>
<simpara><indexterm>
<primary>gists</primary><secondary>and RESTful APIs</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>and RESTful APIs</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm>
<primary>RESTful APIs</primary>
</indexterm>Most RESTful APIs come with<indexterm>
<primary>sitemaps</primary>
</indexterm> a "sitemap," generally an API reference
document that tells a user which endpoints to use. You view
the resources available from that API and then apply some HTTP verb to
do something to them. Hypermedia thinks of an API differently.
Hypermedia APIs describe themselves inside their responses <indexterm>
<primary>affordances</primary>
</indexterm>using
"affordances." What this means is that the API might respond like this:</simpara>
<programlisting language="json" linenumbering="unnumbered">{
    "_links": {
        "self": {
            "href": "http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920030300.do"
        }
    }
    "id": "xrd",
    "name": "Chris Dawson"
}</programlisting>
<simpara>In this payload, you can see that there is an id ("xrd") and a name
("Chris Dawson"). This particular payload was forked from the HAL explanation at the
<link xl:href="http://bit.ly/1SGLDw3">HAL
Primer document</link>, and you can find a more detailed explanation of these concepts
there.</simpara>
<simpara>The important thing to note about hypermedia APIs is that payloads contain
metadata about data itself and metadata about the possible options of
operating on the data. RESTful APIs typically provide a mapping
outside of the payload. You have to join the API sitemap with the data
in an ad hoc way when using RESTful APIs; with hypermedia APIs your
client can react to the payload itself correctly and intelligently
without knowing anything about a sitemap stored in human-readable
documentation.</simpara>
<simpara>This loose coupling makes APIs and their clients flexible. In theory,
a hypermedia API works intuitively with a hypermedia-aware client. If
you change the API, the client, as it understands hypermedia, can
react and still work as expected. Using a RESTful API means that
clients must be updated (a newer version of the client must be
installed) or the client code must be upgraded. Hypermedia APIs can
alter their backend, and then the client, as long as it is
hypermedia-aware, can automatically and dynamically determine
the right way to access information from the response itself. In other
words, with a hypermedia client the API backend can change and your
client code should not need to.</simpara>
<simpara>This is explained in great detail in the book <a class="orm:hideurl" href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920020530.do"><em>Building
Hypermedia APIs with HTML5 and Node</em> (O'Reilly)</a>.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_using_hypermedia_data_from_octokit">
<title>Using Hypermedia Data from Octokit</title>
<simpara><indexterm>
<primary>gists</primary><secondary>using hypermedia data from Octokit</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>using hypermedia data from Octokit</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm>
<primary>hypermedia data, Octokit</primary>
</indexterm><indexterm>
<primary>Octokit</primary><secondary>using hypermedia data from</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>using hypermedia data from</primary>
</indexterm>Now that you know a little about hypermedia, let&#8217;s navigate it using Octokit:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>Start at a resource, with code like <literal>user = Octokit.user "xrd"</literal>. This
begins the initialization of the client.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><literal>user</literal> now is an object filled with the actual data of the resource.
In this case, you could call a method like <literal>user.followers</literal> to see a
meager follower count.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara><literal>user</literal> also has hypermedia references. You can see these by calling
<literal>user.rels</literal>. This retrieves the relationships described in the
hypermedia links.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Relationships (found by calling <literal>user.rels</literal>) include avatar, self,
followers, etc.</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Use a relationship by calling the <literal>get.data</literal> method to retrieve and
access the data from the GitHub API (<literal>followers =
user.rels[:followers].get.data</literal>).</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>Calling <literal>.get.data</literal> populates an array of the followers (paged if it
exceeds 100 items).</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>Let&#8217;s extend our Sinatra app to retrieve actual data about the user&#8217;s
gists by using hypermedia references:</simpara>
<programlisting language="ruby" linenumbering="unnumbered">require 'sinatra'
require 'octokit'

set :views, "."

helpers do
  def h(text)
    Rack::Utils.escape_html(text)
  end
end

get '/:username' do |username|
  gists = Octokit.gists username, :per_page =&gt; 5
  erb :index, locals: { :gists =&gt; gists, username: username }
end</programlisting>
<simpara>The <emphasis>index.erb</emphasis> file contains code to iterate over each gist and pull
the content. You can see that our response object is an array of
gists, and each has an attribute called <literal>fields</literal>. This <literal>fields</literal> attribute
specifies the filenames available in each gist. If you reference that
filename against the files, the response includes a hypermedia <literal>ref</literal>
attribute. Retrieve the <literal>raw</literal> content using the Octokit method <literal>.get.data</literal>:</simpara>
<programlisting language="html" linenumbering="unnumbered">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;body&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;User &lt;%= username %&gt;'s last five gists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;% gists.each do |g| %&gt;
&lt;% g[:files].fields.each do |f| %&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;%= f %&gt;&lt;/b&gt;:

&lt;%= h g[:files][f.to_sym].rels[:raw].get.data %&gt;

&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;% end %&gt;
&lt;% end %&gt;

&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>
<simpara>Now we see the gists and the contents, as in <xref linkend="last_five_gists_with_details"/>.<indexterm>
<primary>range=endofrange</primary><secondary>startref=ix_chapter-02-gist-asciidoc1</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>startref=ix_chapter-02-gist-asciidoc1</primary>
</indexterm></simpara>
<figure xml:id="last_five_gists_with_details">
<title>Last five gists, with details</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="images/btwg_02in03.png"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>btwg 02in03</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</section>
</section>
<section xml:id="_summary">
<title>Summary</title>
<simpara>In this chapter we looked at gists and learned how they can be used
to share code snippets. We built a simple application and stored it as
a gist. This application retrieves data from the GitHub API using our
first higher-level language client library (the Octokit library for
Ruby). We also went deeper into how hypermedia works and how a client
library implements using hypermedia metadata.<indexterm>
<primary>range=endofrange</primary><secondary>startref=ix_chapter-02-gist-asciidoc0</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>startref=ix_chapter-02-gist-asciidoc0</primary>
</indexterm></simpara>
<simpara>In the next chapter we will look at Gollum, the GitHub wiki. This
chapter provides an introduction to the Rugged Ruby library for accessing Git
repositories and the Ruby library for accessing GitHub.</simpara>
</section>
</section>
</article>